Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Labour Party (Great Britain) PE.034
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Labour Party (Great Britain)
1910-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.034
2 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The Tamiment Library, New York University, founded in 1906 as the library of the Rand School of Social Science, is a special collection documenting the history of United States radicalism, labor, and progressive social action. It accumulated this artificial collection of printed ephemera gradually over the years. The Printed Ephemera Collection on the Labour Party (Great Britain) consists of fliers, newspaper clippings, reports, pamphlets, publications, and other printed ephemera.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into one series, chronologically and then alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Labour Party of Great Britain formed around the turn of the 20th century in response to the need to represent the interests and needs of working-class people. The party grew out of the trade union movement and socialist political parties of the 19th century seeking these workers' representation. In 1900 the Trades Union Congress and the Independent Labour Party (founded 1893) established the Labour Representation Committee, which took the name Labour Party in 1906.
The Labour party came to power for the first time in 1924 and again in 1929. The party survives today as one of the leading political parties in England.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents activities and events of the British Labour Party from 1910 and on. The collection consists of memoranda, newspaper clippings, convention materials, and constitutions, as well as a pamphlets and publications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
Pamphlets.; Socialists |z England.; Constitutions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Political parties |z Great Britain.; Proceedings.; Labour Party (Great Britain)
- 1910-1919 (Box 1)
- 1920-1929 I (Box 1)
- 1920-1929 II (Box 1)
- 1930-1935 I (Box 1)
- 1930-1935 II (Box 1)
- 1930-1935 III (Box 1)
- 1936-1937 I (Box 1)
- 1936-1937 II (Box 1)
- 1937: Commission of Inquiry into the Destressed Areas (pamphlets) (Box 1)
- 1938-1939 I (Box 1)
- 1938-1939 II (Box 1)
- 1940-1943 I (Box 1)
- 1940-1943 II (Box 1)
- 1944-1947 I (Box 1)
- 1944-1947 II (Box 1)
- 1948-1949 I (Box 1)
- 1948-1949 II (Box 1)
- 1950-1952 I (Box 1)
- 1950-1952 II (Box 1)
- 1953-1959 I (Box 1)
- 1953-1959 II (Box 2)
- 1960-1969 (Box 2)
- 1970-2000, undated (Box 2)
- Bibliography, 1967 (Box 2)
- Conference/Convention, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
- Conference/Convention, 1921, 1931 (Box 2)
- Conference/Convention, 1933-1944 (Box 2)
- Conference/Convention, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
- Conference/Convention, 1960, 1978 (Box 2)
- Constitution, 1918, undated (Box 2)
- General articles/newspaper clippings, undated (Box 2)
- Kent County Council, 1954 (Box 2)
- National Conference of Labour Women, 1925-1969 (Box 2)
- Pamphlets I, undated (Box 2)
- Pamphlets II, undated (Box 2)
- "Towards Tomorrow" pamphlets, undated (Box 2)